Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Facilitators' Chronological Files, 1983-2001; 3.0 Linear Feet 6 boxes
  - Inside Line [New Day Films internal newsletter], 1986 March-1988 May (Box 56)
    Monthly internal newsletter. Includes first issue of March 1986.
  - Mailing list and database manager search, RFPs, 1986-1988 (Box 56)
  - Film coding, 1987-1988 (Box 56)
    Includes proposal for new coding system for New Day from Durrin Films.
  - Meeting notes, 1987-1990 (Box 56)
    Chiefly from 1987 meetings; includes a fax from 1990. Oversize item has been removed.
  - Planning timeline on very large sheet, circa 1987 November (Oversize-folder 1)
    Very large timeline starting for the last quarter of 1987 and continuing into 1988.
  - Prospectuses for New Day Films and New Day Educational Media (NDEM), 1987-1991 (Box 56)
  - Strategic planning, 1988 May (Box 56)
  - West Glen distributors, 1988 June-August (Box 56)
  - Personnel: Durin resignation, 1988 June-October (Box 56)
  - Doing It Yourself [book by New Day members] memos and planning, 1988 (Box 56)
  - Activity/transactions, 1988-1989 (Box 56)
  - Business plan draft for 1988-1989, correspondence, and related documents, 1974-1981, 1988-1989 (Box 56)
    Earlier dates refer to historical supporting documents.
  - Personnel: Rottersman [Central Office manager], 1989 January-October (Box 56)
  - Personnel: Mondell / Rutledge, 1989 April-May (Box 56)
  - Software proposals, 1989 May (Box 56)
  - Women's Issues and Global Perspectives subgroups brochures and notes, 1989 June-November (Box 56)
  - Meeting notes, 1989 (Box 56)
  - New film response forms, 1989 (Box 56)
  - Correspondence and other materials about issues with Community Media Productions (CMP) and film Man Oh Man, 1989-1990 (Box 57)
  - Reports about Central Office, 1990 May (Box 57)
  - State of the Co-op report, 1990 May (Box 57)
  - Inside Line [New Day newsletter], 1990 June-August (Box 57)
  - Correspondence on video pricing, "Thin Grey Line" and other brief reports, meeting notes, 1990 July-October (Box 57)
    "The Thin Grey Line" was an informal letter sharing information about various filmmaker's activities, thoughts, and whereabouts. May be related to the Steering Committee.
  - Desktop publishing report, membership lists, and various correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 57)
  - New Day workshops and other programs, 1990-1991 (Box 57)
  - Resources and brochures by New Day and other organizations, 1990s (Box 57)
  - 20th anniversary materials, 1991 January-1992 January (Box 57)
  - Corporate by-laws, annotated draft, 1991 May 5 (Box 57)
  - 1991 Annual Meeting: agendas, correspondence, panel reports after the meeting, 1991 May-June (Box 57)
  - First Night Circle notes (Annual Meeting), 1991 June (Box 57)
  - Personnel: Cooper agreement/contract, 1991 June-November (Box 57)
  - Midyear Steering Committee meeting, New Day Films Task report, and meeting notes, 1991 August-November (Box 57)
  - Memory Film project, 1991 November 25 (Box 57)
  - Future plans: questionnaire, reports, and correspondence on member concerns, 1991 November-1992 April (Box 57)
  - American Airlines Air Travel card information, 1991 (Box 57)
  - Telemarketing, proposal for National Video Resources (NVR) and New Day grant, 1991 (Box 57)
  - New Day internal workshop/policy presentation: "Cultural Policy", 1992 May (Box 57)
  - Telemarketing pilot: results summary, 1992 May (Box 57)
  - 20th anniversary: report on promotion, 1992 November (Box 57)
  - Member issues, including outreach, shares, various reports and correspondence, 1992 January-1993 June (Box 57)
  - National Video Resources (NVR) Distributor Assistance Program proposal, 1992 September-December (Box 57)
  - Steering Committee minutes, 1992 November (Box 57)
  - Marketing consultant report (Mark Freeman), 1992 November-1993 May (Box 57)
  - Member list, 1992 December 28 (Box 57)
  - Financial reports, 1992 December-1993 February (Box 57)
  - Steering Committee conference call, 1993 January (Box 57)
  - Steering Committee conference call, 1993 April (Box 58)
  - Transit Media proposal, 1993 May 22 (Box 58)
  - Activity/shares reports, 1993 May (Box 58)
  - Annual Meeting "Futures" and "Big questions" sessions planning, 1993 May (Box 58)
  - Annual meeting, 1993 June (Box 58)
  - NDF report regarding distribution in Japan, standardized cassette covers, 1993 June (Box 58)
  - Future scenarios from Tim Schwab, 1993 September (Box 58)
  - Member list, 1993 October-November (Box 58)
  - Proposals on policy changes (various), 1993 October-November (Box 58)
    Proposals refer to policies on pre-screening, member contracts, promotion, and other topics.
  - Task report, thoughts on chair position, correspondence, meeting notes, 1993 November-1994 May (Box 58)
  - Films: screenings and correspondence, 1993 (Box 58)
  - Steering Committee minutes, 1994 June (Box 58)
  - Personnel: Terms of agreement for Gene Meyer, and Transit Media contract, 1994 June-October (Box 58)
    Includes correspondence as well as drafts of agreements and contracts.
  - New membership application (drafts) and other correspondence, 1994 July-October (Box 58)
  - Steering Committee call, 1994 July 30 (Box 58)
  - National Video Resources (NVR) proposal, 1994 August-September (Box 58)
  - Steering Committee call minutes, 1994 October 8 (Box 58)
  - Steering Committee meeting, 1994 October-November (Box 58)
  - Member and task force reports and proposals, 1994 November-1995 June (Box 58)
    Proposals from members include: drop shipping, home video sales policy; free preview policy; online task force; Steering Committee Compensation. Also includes Task Report on debt collection.
  - Steering Committee tasks, 1994 November (Box 58)
  - Steering Committee meeting minutes, 1994 November (Box 58)
  - General policies, 1994 November (Box 58)
  - Meeting notes on promotional/outreach budget, oversize sheet, circa 1993 (Oversize-folder 1)
    From a large group of loose meeting minutes and notes with dates around 1993.
  - Member correspondence, 1994 (Box 59)
  - Member list, 1994 (Box 59)
  - Financial reports, 1994-1995 (Box 59)
  - Finances/shares, 1995 January (Box 59)
  - Steering Committee conference call, 1995 January (Box 59)
  - Steering Committee conference call, 1995 April (Box 59)
  - State of the Co-op and market reports, 1995 May (Box 59)
  - Member agenda, 1995 May (Box 59)
  - 1995 Annual Meeting materials, 1995 June (Box 59)
    Includes draft agenda, meeting notes, reports, a few film publicity brochures, and correspondence.
  - Recruitment, 1995 June (Box 59)
  - Steering Committee agenda, 1995 June (Box 59)
  - Task report, 1995 June (Box 59)
  - General policies, 1995 June (Box 59)
  - Email lists, 1995 June-August (Box 59)
  - Membership issues, 1995 June-November (Box 59)
    Materials include a report on recruiting new members; a report on membership inquiries; and a chart of membership status and related benefits.
  - Share system "ladder", 1995 July-November (Box 59)
  - Committee reports/proposals, 1995 September-October (Box 59)
    Submitted in advance of a Steering Committee meeting, reports are typically one page and include computing; distribution; and a proposal to designate a Collections person.
  - Steering Committee agenda, 1995 October 1 (Box 59)
  - New films: proposals, correspondence, outreach, 1995 August-December (Box 59)
  - Task report, 1995 October-November (Box 59)
  - Promotion and computer report, 1995 November (Box 59)
  - Steering Committee minutes, 1995 November 9 (Box 59)
  - Promotion, 1995 (Box 59)
  - Financial reports, 1995-1996 (Box 59)
  - Finance/activity, 1995-1996 (Box 59)
  - Promotion, 1995-1996 (Box 59)
  - Recruitment and new film submissions, 1996 May (Box 59)
  - Other reports/proposals, 1996 May (Box 59)
    Includes member proposal related to resignation policies; other items include a computer report, new film submissions, and State of the Co-op report.
  - Membership/status, 1996 May (Box 59)
  - Transit Media / USA Dubs, 1996 May (Box 59)
  - Annual meeting site information, 1996 May (Box 59)
  - Steering Committee agendas, 1996 June (Box 59)
  - Website Task Force report, 1996 June (Box 59)
  - 25th anniversary: publicity and emails, 1995-1996 (Box 60)
    Copy of 25th anniversary catalog removed to Printed Materials series oversize box.
  - 25th anniversary New Day Films catalog, 1995-1996 (Box 64)
  - Reports, correspondence, notes, 1996 (Box 60)
    Includes short report on state of independent distributors and the market.
  - Task report, 1996 (Box 60)
  - Field reports, community outreach reports, 1997 May-June (Box 60)
  - Distribution policies, 1997 June (Box 60)
  - Proposals, reports, correspondence, 1997 September (Box 60)
    Several items are requests for membership status change; other correspondence comes from annual meeting topics.
  - Steering Committee agenda draft, 1997 October (Box 60)
  - Steering Committee agenda and related items, 1997 October (Box 60)
  - State of the Co-op report, 1997 November (Box 60)
  - Promotion, 1997 November (Box 60)
  - Task report, 1997 November (Box 60)
  - Video duplication correspondence, 1997 December-1998 May (Box 60)
  - Various reports, 1998 May-July (Box 60)
    includes report on activities of consultant firm Adams & Goldbard, as well as requests for membership status changes, State of the Co-op document, and a proposal and comments concerning the Independent Television Service (ITVS) contract and funding. ITVS was established through legislation by the United States Congress in 1988, to fund and present documentary programming and films on public television primarily through distribution by PBS and American Public Television.
  - Membership list, 1999 January 25 (Box 60)
  - Workshop, internal: Interpersonal skills and group dynamics, typewritten outline, one sheet, 1990s? (Box 60)
  - Committee reports/proposals, 2000 May (Box 60)
    Includes State of Co-op report, requests for membership status changes, and a report on state of independent distributors and the market.
  - 30th Anniversary correspondence, 2001 January-February (Box 60)
  - Futures Committee correspondence and computer report, 2001 February-April (Box 60)
  - Thin Grey Line member updates [New Day newsletter], 2001 Winter (Box 60)
    This internal membership newsletter contains a list of narrative updates from 34 filmmakers about their professional (and sometimes personal) activities. Most are one paragraph, but others are longer.
- Printed Materials, 1971-2015; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes
  Series is organized into three groups: a collection of New Day film and video catalogs; journals and magazines with articles related to feminist artists, independent film and video distribution, filmmaking, and other related topics; and printed publicity and other items such as ephemera. Within groups, items are organized by date.
  - New Day Films Catalogs, 1972-2015
    Folders contain an almost complete run of New Day film and video catalogs arranged chronologically from its earliest years to 2015. Includes several anniversary catalogs; the last folder contains catalogs devoted to subgroup topics such as history, culture, diversity, gender, health, relationships, and educational films; as well as a few catalogs from other organizations.
    - Film and video catalogs, 1972-2015; 5 folders (Box 61)
    - Film and video subject group catalogs, circa 1987-circa 2011 (Box 61)
      These catalogs and brochures related to topical subgroups created by New Day Films. These include: Women, History, and Sexuality.
  - Journals, Magazines, Newsletters, 1973-1983, 1996, 2005, 2011
    Folders contain whole issues of mainstream magazines or professional journals with articles related to general topics such as filmmaking, women filmmakers, feminism, and the arts and social change. Arranged chronologically.
    - Esquire [men's magazine]: "This Issue is About Women", 1973 July (Box 62)
    - Media and Methods, 1974 October (Box 62)
    - Women and Film, 1975 (Box 62)
    - Filmmakers Newsletter, 1976 November (Box 62)
    - Filmmakers Newsletter, 1976 November (Box 62)
    - Filmmakers Newsletter, 1977 September (Box 62)
    - Ms.: "The Arts Explosion Will Change Your Life" arts issue, 1977 December (Box 62)
    - Booklist, 1981 April 1 (Box 62)
    - Learning, 1982 January (Box 62)
    - Ms., 1982 October (Box 62)
    - The Progressive, 1983 January (Box 62)
    - The Independent Film and Video Monthly, 1996 May (Box 62)
    - Release Print, 2005 September-October (Box 62)
    - Filmmaker, 2011 (Box 62)
  - Other Printed Materials, 1971-2011
    Folders contain an assortment of printed materials produced by New Day Films cooperative to aid in publicity, distribution, and communications. Includes brochures, many fliers, a calendar, and a few stickers. Some of the items relate to other organizations. Also includes a copy of the New Day handbook on independent film distribution (1977). Folders are arranged in alphabetical order by title. Other related and overlapping materials, particularly promotional pieces, are found in founders' files and in the Cooperative Files series.
    - Calendar (one sheet), and stickers with New Day logo and website address, 1981 and after 1996 (Box 62)
    - Doing it Yourself: A Handbook on Independent Film Distribution, 1977 February (Box 62)
      Written and published by New Day members.
    - Film fliers and brochures, 1980s-2000s; Folders 1-3 of 4 (Box 62)
      Publicity items for New Day films, typically sent out in mass mailings.
    - Film fliers and brochures, 1980s-2000s; Folder 4 of 4 (Box 63)
    - Mail-in order form, 1975 (Box 63)
    - Mailings, 1996-2009; 3 folders (Box 63)
    - Oversize poster: New Day / Films About Women: "first poster", 1973 (Oversize-folder 1)
      The first New Day poster, noted as the only copy in existence. The poster was intended to be folded up into a mailer. The design features purple and white lettering on orange background.
    - New Day poster - designs and copy, 1973 (Box 63)
    - Newsletters, 1972-2001 (Box 63)
    - Other fliers and brochures, 1971-1980 and undated (Box 63)
      Includes mailers and brochures advertising New Day Films. Publicity for individual films is found in the "Film fliers" folders.
    - Oversize New Day Films poster, after 1977 (Box 65)
    - Oversize posters for film festivals (2), undated (Box 65)
    - Resource books and guides to films, independent film distributors, and film-making, circa 1972-2016 (Box 63)
      Titles include: A report on the status of independent film in the United States; The AIVF guide to film and video distributors (Association of Independent Video and Filmmakers); and A guide to film about women and change.
    - Study guides for New Day Films, 1980-1994 (Box 63)
      Study guides produced by New Day or by others: Once Upon a Choice; To Have and to Hold; In Our Water; Becoming American; The Last Pullman Car; If the Mango Tree Could Speak; and Kicking High In the Golden Years.
- Digital Films Collection, 1971-2018; 12 Terabytes 214 digital files
  Arrangement
  Arranged in alphabetical order by filmmaker's last name, then by date.
  Two hundred fourteen digital files of films released by New Day Films, representing 103 filmmakers. Description provided by New Day Films and taken from New Day Films website, https://www.newday.com/, June 2019.
  Lower resolution user copies are available for viewing in the reading room; higher resolution preservation copies are available but may require special permissions for access and use.
  Please contact Rubenstein Library Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Abt, Emily
    - Take It From Me, 2001; 75 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0004_u, Video-file AbtEmily_TakeItFromMe.mp4)
      Captured over two years, Take It From Me is a feature-length documentary about four women struggling against great odds to raise themselves and their families out of poverty in New York City.
    - All Of Us, 2008; 82 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0004_u, Video-file AbtEmily_AllOfUs.mp4)
      A young doctor in the South Bronx embarks on a project to find out why African-American women are becoming infected with HIV at alarming rates. She finds a dangerous power imbalance that all heterosexual women face in the bedroom, but rarely discuss. Selected as Showtime's 2008 World AIDS Day Film.
    - Toe To Toe, 2010; 104 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0004_u, Video-file AbtEmily_ToeToToe.mp4)
      Toe to Toe tells the story of the friendship and rivalry between lacrosse teammates Tosha and Jesse, two senior girls at a competitive Washington, D.C. prep school. The two forge a close bond on the lacrosse field, but their friendship unravels as they navigate through gender, sexuality, race and class-related obstacles.
    - Daddy Don't Go, 2015; 87 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0004_u, Video-file AbtEmily_DaddyDontGo.mp4)
      Captured over two years, "Daddy Don't Go" is a feature length documentary about four disadvantaged fathers in New York City as they struggle to beat the odds and defy the deadbeat dad stereotype.
  - Acosta, Katherine
    - Divided We Fall, 2016; 90 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0005_u, Video-file AcostaKatherine_DividedWeFall.mp4)
      The first film to take a critical look at the 2011 Wisconsin Uprising, Divided We Fall traces the genesis of the historic capitol occupation and weeks-long protests from the perspective of graduate teaching assistants at the center of the action and exposes tensions that challenged the movement's solidarity.
  - Anderson, Kelly
    - Out At Work, 1999/2009; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0006_u, Video-file AndersonKelly_OutAtWork.mp4)
      In 1992 Cheryl Summerville, a cook at a Cracker Barrel restaurant in Georgia, received a termination paper stating she was fired for "failing to demonstrate normal heterosexual values." She was shocked to discover that in more than 40 states it was legal to fire workers for their sexual orientation. OUT AT WORK chronicles the stories of three workers who seek workplace safety, job security and benefits for gay and lesbian workers. Also on this DVD: OUT AT WORK: America Undercover, an HBO special featuring the shocking story of a stock trader's harassment at Cantor Fitzgerald. Both versions of this classic documentary include 2009 updates.
    - Every Mother's Son, 2004; 52 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0006_u, Video-file AndersonKelly_EveryMothersSon.mp4)
      Iris Baez, a Puerto Rican from the Bronx, never meant to become an activist. Kadiatou Diallo never meant to leave her home in Africa and move to the U.S., to fight for justice for her son. Doris Busch Boskey, a Jewish woman from the suburbs, never thought she'd become a spokesperson against police brutality. This film profiles three women from very different walks of life who find themselves united to seek justice after their sons are unjustly killed by police. Their stories are tragic, but their courage is transformative.
    - Never Enough, 2010; 39 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0006_u, Video-file AndersonKelly_NeverEnough.mp4)
      Michele Gitlin has 700 sweaters. In touch with the pain as well as the pleasure of over-collecting, she calls Ron "Disaster Master" Alford for help. Ron, a de-cluttering expert who believes that "clutter begins in the head, and ends up on the floor," determines that Michele is a hoarder with a rating of 8 (out of ten) on his "clutter index." Ron also visits a retired Marine with 7,800 Beanie Babies and a home shopping addict whose purchases are literally burying him. Produced by Kelly Anderson.
    - My Brooklyn, 2012; 77 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0006_u, Video-file AndersonKelly_MyBrooklyn.mp4)
      My Brooklyn follows director Kelly Anderson's journey, as a Brooklyn gentrifier, to understand the forces reshaping her neighborhood. Produced by Allison Lirish Dean & Kelly Anderson.
    - Unstuck: An OCD Kids Movie, 2017; 22 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0006_u, Video-file AndersonKelly_Unstuck.mp4)
      Six kids with OCD share how they learned to face their fears, stop their rituals and regain control of their lives.
  - Argueta, Luis
    - Abrazos, 2014; 45 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0007_u, Video-file ArguetaLuis_Abrazos.mp4)
      ABRAZOS tells the transformational journey of a group of U.S. Citizen Children, sons and daughters of undocumented immigrants, who travel from Minnesota to Guatemala to meet their grandparents -and in some instances their siblings - for the first time. There are 4.5 million other U.S. citizen children who, like them, have at least one undocumented parent and are part of mixed-status families, ABRAZOS is the story of 14 of them.
  - Arnold, Robert
    - The Key Of G, 2007; 59 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0008_u, Video-file ArnoldRobert_TheKeyOfG.mp4)
      The Key of G is an award-winning documentary about disability, caregiving and interdependence. The film follows Gannet, a charismatic 22-year-old with physical and developmental disabilities, as he leaves his mother's home to share an apartment with a close-knit group of artists and musicians who support him, not only as paid caregivers, but also as friends. Together they create a uniquely successful model of supported living, and a compelling alternative to institutionalized care. Produced by Lindsay Sablosky.
  - Avila-Hanna, Brenda
    - Vida Diferida, 2013; 23 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0009_u, Video-file AvilaHannaBrenda_VidaDiferida.mp4)
      After the announcement of the policy known as "Deferred Action", Vanessa, an undocumented teenager, contemplates the possibility of a future she was ready to give up on. How will this life-changing opportunity impact her life and the lives of those around her?
  - Beraza, Suzan
    - Bag It, 2010; 78 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0010_u, Video-file BerazaSuzan_BagIt.mp4)
      Try going a day without plastic. In this touching and often flat-out-funny film, we follow "everyman" Jeb Berrier as he embarks on a global tour to unravel the complexities of our plastic world.
    - Uranium Drive-In, 2013; 70 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0010_u, Video-file BerazaSuzan_UraniumDriveIn.mp4)
      Uranium Drive-In follows a proposed uranium mill in southwestern Colorado -- the first to be built in the U.S. in 30 years -- and the emotional debate pitting a population desperate for jobs and financial stability against an environmental group based in a nearby resort town. Without judgment, both sides of the issue are brought to life in heart-wrenching detail as the film follows conflicting visions for the future. The film offers no easy answers but aims instead to capture personal stories and paint a portrait of the lives behind this nuanced and complex issue. Produced by Michelle Maughan, Judith Kohin, Casey Nay, Suzan Beraza.
  - Bezalel, Ronit
    - 70 Acres in Chicago, 2017; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0011_u, Video-file BezalelRonit_70AcresinChicago.mp4)
      Filmed over a period of 20-years, 70 Acres in Chicago: Cabrini Green chronicles the demolition of Chicago's most infamous public housing development, Cabrini Green, the displacement of residents, and the subsequent area gentrification. This complex, poignant film looks unflinchingly at race, class, and survival.
  - Booth, Marlene
    - Raananah A World Of Our Own, 1981; 28 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0012_u, Video-file BoothMarlene_RaananahAWorldOfOurOwn.mp4)